{
  "reference_number": "12845",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Carbon Dioxide - Reducing net carbon dioxide emissions to zero by 2050",
      "answer_index": 13,
      "notes": "The Paris Agreement is more inclusive in that it sets aspirations for developing as well as developed countries. Many developing\n countries have a green house gas profile which has a significant proportion coming from biological emissions (Methane and Nitrous\n\n Oxide). Key to the Paris agreement is that is recognizes that, as well as mitigating global warming, we also have a growing population\n who needs to be fed. Starvation is not a just means of population control but security and an increased standard of living is.\n Population growth has slowed to reversed in many developed countries and the greatest contribution to population growth is in\n\n Africa who have yet to feel the real benefits of good government and a secure food supply. Of course New Zealand will not feed the\n world but it is naive and misleading to suggest that what we produce does not make a contribution to that goal. The Paris Agreement\n recognizes this in that it says in its preamble: \"Recognizing the fundamental priority of safeguarding food security and ending\n\n hunger..\" and in its text says: \"....foster .....low green house gas emissions development, in a manner that does not threaten food\n production\". My experience as the Acting President of the World Farmers Organisation has shown me that farmers (including livestock\n\n farmers) care about climate change and the threat it may bring to them but they also are ready and willing to play their part in\n mitigation. This is reflected in the policy adopted by the General Assembly of WFO (http://www.wfo-\n oma.org/media/k2/attachments/policy-climatechange-agriculture_1.pdf). I would also note the cumulative nature of Carbon Dioxide\n\n and the short lived nature of methane and the priorities that scientists such as Victoria University's Prof David Frame have put on\n carbon dioxide. So while I support option one (Net Zero Carbon Dioxide) I consider that if we are to play our part in meeting our\n commitments to the Paris Agreement we should strive for net zero carbon dioxide, principally through the reduced production of CO2\n\n by substitution (electric/hydrogen fueled cars and stationary power) but we should also strive for greater methane and nitrous oxide\n efficiency in our livestock sector. Thus the target should be one of stabilisation of the biological emissions but principally efficiency in\n\n food production across those two gases. To get to net zero biological emissions would mean farmers buying offsets or being taxed\n for their emissions which would simply make New Zealand farmers who are already among the most carbon efficient in the world, less\n competitive and in the extreme would drive the livestock sector which plays such a critical part in our economy to zero. I would also\n\n point out that planting trees, particularly pine trees which will be harvested will only sequester significant carbon until the average\n wood volume is reached after that there is little further benefit over the long term of the forest. Therefore reduction in carbon dioxide\n\n emissions and \"carbon efficiency\" in food production is the most effective approach to achieving a net zero carbon as I have defined\n it. Finally to promote carbon efficiency in food production any any tax or penalty (e.g. ETS) on farmers should be recirculated back to\n promote/research further carbon efficiency rather than subsidising other sectors. most carbon efficient farmers"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "This is a world problem so we should approach it with a world solution and that is trading within a robust system. Noting however my\n points above that real reduction (CO2) and carbon efficiency in food production should be the real goals."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It is impossible to predict the future and governments need to be able to make those changes as science and circumstances\n\nchange. Some may argue that to fix a target in legislation would be the only way to hold governments to the cause but we have seen\nthat both major parties are committed to making a difference in this space."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I have no real opinion on this but I do consider that the temptation would be to set unrealistic targets which inevitably end in failure or\n\nresult in over reaction from the government of the day and resulting in unintended consequences, particularly for the economy and\ntheir own political capital."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Actually I think short term budgets are unrealistic and the big changes are going to come from technological advances (e.g nuclear\nfusion reactors) and this is difficult to predict in the short term. Therefore targets would be better in more practical terms e.g. number\nof electric cars, contribution of solar etc."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "This question is pejorative and indicates the govt already has in its mind an emissions budget over 15 years."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This will be one of the biggest challenges for New Zealand agriculture and our economy."
    }
  ]
}
